<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor and court of aldermen at Guild-Hall-Chappel, July the 23th, 1682 by Thomas Pargiter ...</title>
            <author>Pargiter, Thomas, 1642 or 3-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13167455</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13167455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 432:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor and court of aldermen at Guild-Hall-Chappel, July the 23th, 1682 by Thomas Pargiter ...</title>
                  <author>Pargiter, Thomas, 1642 or 3-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Green ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 1st, IV, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED before the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord MAYOR AND COURT of ALDERMEN, AT <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILD-HALL</hi>-CHAPPEL, <hi>July</hi> the 23<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS PARGITER</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Greetworth</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 THES. 4.6.</bibl> That no Man go beyond and Defraud his Brother in any matter, becauſe that the Lord is the Avenger of all ſuch.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Green,</hi> and are to be Sold by moſt Book ſellers in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98261:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe that which hath made ſeveral Worthy Perſons very Earneſt and Importunate for the Publication of this Sermon, is the exceeding great Honeſty of it, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly Levelled againſt all manner of <hi>Fraudulent</hi> and <hi>Injurious Practices.</hi> In it the great, but very much neglected Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Doing no Harm</hi> or <hi>Wrong to one another,</hi> is as throughly and fully Preſſed upon us, as it could poſſibly be in ſo ſhort a time as is allowed for a Sermon; and the hopes that it may do ſome good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:98261:3"/>the making of Men more <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> in their Dealings than gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they are, hath been the chief and prevailing Cauſe of the Printing of it: And ſurely the ſending abroad of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon this Duty of <hi>not Wronging one another,</hi> cannnot be thought <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable or Impertinent in ſuch times as theſe, wherein the Hearts and the Wits of Men are ſo much ſet upon <hi>doing Wrong.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98261:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED before the Lord Mayor, AT GUILD-HALL <hi>Chappel, July</hi> 23. 1682. ON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 THESS. iv. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>That no man go beyond and Defraud his Brother in any matter, becauſe that the Lord is the Avenger of all ſuch.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE Words will afford us very good and fit Matter for a ſerious, uſeful, and practical Diſcourſe; and that the enſuing Sermon upon them may be altogether ſuch, I ſhall obſerve in them theſe two things.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98261:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. A Duty. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Enforcement of that Duty.</p>
            <p>The Duty here enjoined us by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is, that we muſt not go beyond and Defraud our Brethren in any matter. And this Duty the Apoſtle enforces upon us by ſuch a dreadful Argument, as may well terrifie and affright us all into a careful Performance of it; for he tells us, that if we do go beyond and Defraud our Brethren in any matter, the Lord will be the Avenger of us: God will not then ſuffer us to go Unpuniſhed, but will moſt ſurely Execute his Vengeance upon us.</p>
            <p>There is ſome Controverſie among Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors about the Duty of the Text, and they are not fully agreed what it is that St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here enjoyn us, when he chargeth us not to go beyond and Defraud our Brethren in any matter. Some of the ancient Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and a late Learned one of our own, do here very much contract and ſtraiten the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſignification of the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we tranſlate <hi>go beyond</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud,</hi> and in this place reſtrain and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſence of them only to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Uncleanneſſe, and think that that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98261:4"/>which the Apoſtle here enjoins us, is, that we muſt not injure and wrong our Brethren in the matter of Uncleanneſs, either by Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their Bed, or by drawing them to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch unnatural Filthineſſes with us, as are not to be named: And that which chiefly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to make this Interpretation of the Words, is St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſpeaking againſt the Sin of Uncleanneſs, both before the Text, and alſo immediately after it. But notwithſtanding this, the generality of Ancient and Modern Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors do not think fit thus to ſtraiten the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Words, nor ſee reaſon enough to make ſuch a narrow and ſcanty Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text, as if it reſpected only the matter of Uncleanneſs: But they take the words in a larger and more general Sence, as they may be Applied to any Matter or Buſineſs whatſoever that we may have with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo make the meaning of the Text to be, That we muſt not tranſgreſs and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Bounds of Juſtice in our Dealings with one another, we muſt not go beyond and over-reach our Brethren in any matter; we muſt not Defraud and Circumvent others in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing whatſoever; we muſt not any wayes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98261:5"/>wrong them, nor in any kind be Injurious to them. And in this Sence ſurely the Words may well be underſtood, and we ſhall the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believe that this is the right meaning of them, if we do but conſider that this Duty of not Wronging and Defrauding our Brethren, is a thing that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was very ſtrict and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in Preſſing upon others, and in Practiſing himſelf: He chides the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes them ſharply for their Neglect of this Duty, and ſeems to upbraid them with a great deal of Indignation for their breach of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Nay, you do wrong and Defraud, and that your Brethren.</hi> Nay, in the foregoing Verſe of that Chapter, he Preſſes this Duty farther and with more ſtrictneſs upon them, than moſt men are now willing to hear of; for he is there ſo far from allowing them to do any injury to others, that he earneſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades them rather to take Wrong, rather to ſuffer themſelves to be Defrauded, rather to loſe ſomething of their own Right, than to go to Law with others upon every Treſpaſs and Offence. And to ſhew theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> how rigid and ſtrict he himſelf had been in the Performance of this Duty, and how clear he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98261:5"/>had alwayes kept himſelf from unjuſt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt dealing with others, he ſolemnly Proteſts to them his own Innocency in this matter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. He there waſhes his Hands clean before them from the doing of any wrong, and lets them know that no unjuſt Gain had ever cleaved to his Fingers; <hi>Recieve us,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>we have wronged no man, we have Defrauded no Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall take it for granted then, that the meaning of the Text is that which our own and moſt other Tranſlations ſpeak it to be, and that the Duty enjoined us here is to this effect; That we muſt not Encroach upon the Rights of our Brethren, nor Defraud them of their Subſtance, nor Injure them at all in any of their Poſſeſſions, but muſt ſuffer them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their own Goods in all quietneſs and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. We muſt not take Advantage of the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or Unwarineſs, the Unskilfulneſs or Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity of others, to beguile them and do them wrong; we muſt not ſtretch our Wits and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to hurt them, nor any wayes to over-reach and Circumvent them in our Dealings with them; we muſt not endeavour by any cunning Devices to take or Detain from them that which is their due; we muſt not uſe any ſubtil Arts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98261:6"/>or Policies either to get or to keep from them that which is their own, and doth of Right belong to them; or in ſhort, We muſt not do any manner of Wrong to them, nor in any thing deal Injuriouſly with them. And that I may the more ſucceſſefully enforce upon you this Duty of not Wronging others, and the more effectually bring you all over to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it, I ſhall handle it both in a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal and in an Applicatory way. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall fully Prove it to you, not only by the Apoſtles, but alſo by ſome other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we muſt not do any manner of Wrong to others, nor in any thing deal Injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly with them. And then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall bring this Duty yet farther home to you by ſome cloſe words of Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall clearly and fully prove it to you, not only by the Apoſtles, but alſo by ſome other Arguments, that we muſt not do any manner of Wrong to others, nor in any thing deal injuriouſly with them. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt not do this, Becauſe that Nature it ſelf teaches us not to do any Injury or Wrong to others. We are not born Wild and Savage Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Beaſts of Prey: We have not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98261:6"/>a Diſpoſition in us to bite, and tear, and devour one another: The State of our Nature is not a State of Rapine and Violence, Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and over-reaching are not any of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of it; as a late Monſter of Men and Shame of Mankind, the great <hi>Leviathan</hi> of Atheiſm, that vile Aſperſer and Slanderer of our Humane Nature, hath ſcurrilouſly aſſerted in his Works, to make way for ſome other of his wretched and forlorn Principles: But on the contrary, our Nature would lead us to all kind of fair and juſt and honeſt Dealings with one another, if we our ſelves did not ſtifle the Dictates, and ſuppreſs the Inclinations of it: Whatſoever the forementioned Traducer of our Nature, or any of his Diſciples may or can ſay to the contrary, we are not left at Liberty by the Principles of our Nature to do what hurt and Miſchief we can to one another; but there are natural Principles of Honeſty written in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Characters upon all our Hearts, that would check, and curb, and reſtrain us from doing wrong, if we were not continually razing them out of our Hearts, by giving way to Pride, and Ambition, and Luſt, and Worldly-mindedneſs; We muſt wink hard, and be wilfully blind,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98261:7"/>blinder than ever the Heathens themſelves could be, if we cannot find a Law of Nature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, that plainly Inſtructs us in this Duty of not wronging others, and ſtrongly Prompts us to the Performance of it. For this Doctrine of doing no Injury or harm to others, is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that was alwayes Currant, not only at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> but at <hi>Athens</hi> too; not only in the Church of God, but alſo in the <hi>Gentile</hi> World: This is a Leſſon that was taught not only in the Schools of the Prophers, but in the Schools of the Philoſophers alſo; a Leſſon that we may learn not only out of the Word of God, but likewiſe out of the Writings of Heathen men; for many of the Heathens themſelves, who had only the Light and the Law of Nature for their Guide, have ſpoken very excellent things of this Duty of not wronging others, and have been very ſerious and earneſt in preſſing the Performance of it, as might eaſily and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly be ſhewed to you out of their Writings: Nay, theſe Gentiles who were meer Strangers to the Grace of God and his written Word, who had nothing elſe but the Dictates of their Nature, and the Principles of their Reaſon, and their In-bred Notions of good and evil to go by,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98261:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>were ſo far from allowing the doing of any injury to one another, that they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them very ſevere Laws againſt <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>Violence,</hi> againſt <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenage,</hi> againſt <hi>Fraud</hi> and <hi>Deceit,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all manner of injurious and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Dealings, and were alſo very ſtrict and punctual in the Execution of thoſe Laws. And therefore we are obliged not to wrong others for this reaſon, becauſe the wronging of them is a plain violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and breach of that very <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> which is written upon all our Hearts, and ſuch a <hi>Sin</hi> as the <hi>Heathens</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who were any waies careful to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of their <hi>Nature,</hi> were quite aſhamed to be guilty of. And let us Chriſtians have a care, and look to it, that the Heathens do not riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us in this matter at the laſt Day, and then in the face and hearing of all the World confound and condemn us in it. But then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> We muſt not do any manner of wrong to others, nor in any thing deal
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98261:8"/>injuriouſly with them, becauſe that this is a thing that is not only taught us by the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> but is expreſly required of us alſo by the Word of God. The Will of God in this matter is ſufficiently re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aled to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o in the Scriptures, and his Commands both in the <hi>Old</hi> and in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> are very full and frequent to this purpoſe, that we muſt not imagine miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in our <hi>Hearts</hi> againſt others, nor do them any wrong, nor injure them at all. The Law of <hi>Wioſes</hi> is plain to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as plain at words can make it, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Defraud thy Neighbour</hi> and again in the Thirty fifth Verſe of that Chapter, <hi>Ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs in Judgment, in Mete-yard, in Weight, or in Meaſure,</hi> that is, Ye ſhall not allow of any manner of falſhood and wrong amongſt you, nor give way to any kind of Fraud and Deceit whatſoever in any of your Dealings and concerns with one another.</p>
            <p>And perhaps this <hi>Duty</hi> of not wronging others was dearly ſignified to the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98261:8"/>under the <hi>Law,</hi> by the very Nature and Temper of thoſe <hi>Living Creatures</hi> which they were to offer in <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> For none of the Birds of the Air, or Beaſts of the Field were choſen and appointed by God for Sacrifice, but ſuch as were harmleſs and inoffenſive, and of a mild Temper, and of a gentle and good Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: And the appointment of ſuch only for Sacrifice might be to teach the Jews, that they ought to be <hi>Tender-hearted, Loving,</hi> and <hi>Gentle</hi> towards one another, and to live in all peacableneſs together, and to do no hurt, or injury, or wrong to one another.</p>
            <p>And then as for the Prophets, they are very full and expreſs in enjoyning this <hi>Duty</hi> of not doing any wrong, and it would be endleſs to inſtance in places out of them to this purpoſe; for they do all with open and with one Mouth exclaim and inveigh againſt the Jews for thoſe injurious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and unrighteous Dealings which they were given to, and call aloud upon them to lay aſide their unjuſt and fraudulent courſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98261:9"/>and to live uprightly, and deal honeſtly with one another. <hi>All things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12. that is, this is the very ſumm and ſubſtance of that which the <hi>Writers</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> have taught us concerning our <hi>Duty</hi> to one another, that we ſhould carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve amongſt us that great Natural Rule of Equity, <hi>To do as we would be done to;</hi> that as we would not that others ſhould do any injury to us, ſo neither ſhould we do any wrong to them. And this <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of not wronging others is very much improved in the New Teſtament, and our Saviour hath there advanced it to an higher pitch than it was before; for he is there ſo far from giving us leave to do the leaſt wrong to others, that he hath ſtrictly commanded us to be kind to our very enemies, and to do good to thoſe very Perſons that hate us and deal evilly with us, and to ſuffer the greateſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from others, rather than to do the leaſt harm to them: And we may obſerve
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98261:9"/>that moſt of the Precepts delivered by him in his famous Sermon upon the Mount, are ſuch as put us upon a ſevere honeſt courſe of Life, and leave no room at all for any kind of crooked and deceitful dealin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s amongſt us So that now under the Goſpel it is more eſpecially our <hi>Duty</hi> to be of an innocent and harmleſs conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, to live without Guile and Deceit in the World, and to keep our Hands pure and clear from violence and wrong, and from all manner of unjuſt dealing. The ancient Chriſtians that lived in the firſt Ages of the Church, thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtrictly obliged, by the Doctrine of Chriſt to do ſo, as plainly appears by that well known and that often cited account which <hi>Pliny</hi> gave of them in a Letter to <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour, when he had begun a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt them; for in his Letter to that Heathen Emperour he tells him, that all that could be proved againſt his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans was only this, that they uſed at ſet times to meet together early in the Morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day to Worſhip Chriſt; and that they did then bind themſelves not to Rob, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98261:10"/>Steal, or commit Adultery; not to break their Word, or falſiſie their Truſt, or the like. Thus honeſt had theſe former Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans their converſation amongſt the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> thus harmleſly and inoffenſively did they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves in the World; and thus carefully were they to abſtain from the very appearance of doing any wrong; ſo that the Heathens themſelves, who watched for their halting, could find no other fault with them, nor charge any other crime upon them, but only this, that they were Chriſtians. And though the Chriſtians of our daies, to their ſhame be it ſpoken, are in their temper and their carriage very unlike to theſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of old, yet the Doctrine of Chriſt in this matter is ſtill the ſame, and doth as ſtrictly require us to forbear the doing of any wrong, as ever it did them. But farther yet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We muſt not do any manner of wrong to others, nor in any thing deal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly with them; becauſe that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us that we ſhould love them. The loving of one another is the Royal Law of Chriſt, and that which is peculiarly his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98261:10"/>It is indeed an, old Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as old as the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nay, as old as the Law of Nature it ſelf; for long before <hi>Moſes</hi> made it Written Law, God himſelf had made it a branch of the Law of Nature within us. But our Saviour hath now ſo fully inſtructed us in it, and in ſuch a ſpecial and particular manner obliged us to the performance of it, that he, calls it his <hi>New Commandment.</hi> And indeed this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> of loving our Brethren he doth every where in the Goſpel ſo ſtrictly enjoyn us, ſo earneſtly recommend to us, and ſo vehemently preſs upon us, as if he almoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired nothing elſe of, us in compariſon of this. And if it is thus ſtrictly and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably required of us that we ſhould love others, then to be ſure we muſt not any waies wrong them, or be injurious to them: for how can the doing of any wrong to them be any waies conſiſtent with, our loving of them? This would certainly be but a very croſs and untoward way of ſhewing that kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and affection to others, that Chriſt hath Commanded us to have for them. But far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet than this:</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98261:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We muſt not do any manner of wrong to others, not in any thing deal injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with them; Becauſe that it is not only required of us that we ſhould love others, but alſo that we ſhould love them as our ſelves. Indeed that known Precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> reſpects rather the quality than the quantity of our Love towards others, and doth not command a parity but a likeneſs of it; for we are not bound to Love others equally, or ſo much as our ſelves, but with the like manner and kind of Love, that we do our ſelves. Our Love then to others, like the Love to our ſelves, muſt not be falſe, and feigned, and hypocritical; but true and real, and without all manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation. Now if we are commanded to proceed ſo far in our kindneſs, and good will, and affections towards others, as to Love them as truly and ſincerely as we do our ſelves, then it is paſt all doubt that we muſt not do any manner of wrong to them; for there are none of us that Love our ſelves ſo little, as to be willing that any kind of hurt or injury ſhould be done to us. But now,</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98261:11"/>
            <p n="5">5. To make uſe of the Apoſtle's dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Argument, to Enforce this Duty, and ſet it fully home upon you: We muſt not do any manner of Wrong to others, nor in any Matter whatſoever deal Injuriouſly with them; Becauſe that the Lord will be the <hi>Avenger of all ſuch.</hi> There is not one of all thoſe that do ſo, that ſhall eſcape the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, and go away unpuniſhed; For the God that is above them, doth narrowly obſerve all the Fraudulent Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which they take, and all the Injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practiſes which they uſe to the hurt of Others, and will in due time call them to a very ſtrick and ſevere Account for them, and fully pay them that which they have Deſerved.</p>
            <p>They that break through all the Bounds of Equity and Juſtice to go beyond and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-reach their Neighbours, that uſe any ſubtile Arts and Devices to defraud their Brethren of their Poſſeſſions, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to encreaſe their own Subſtance, by the Spoil which they make of other men,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98261:12"/>are ſuch Tranſgreſſors as God is highly Diſpleaſed with, and doth uſually ſooner or later Plague even here in this World, as well as in the World to come. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he ſends his ſecret Curſe into their Houſes, which there ſticks faſt by them and like a Canker eats into their Eſtates' and waſtes away their Goods, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees devours and conſumes all that they have. And ſometimes he cauſes the Hand of Publick Juſtice to find them out, and to pluck the Spoil out of their Teeth, and to gripe them, and handle them roughly, and make them Vomit up thoſe forbidden Morſels, thoſe Morſels of Violence and Deceit, which they had ſo glibly devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>And ſometimes, nay oftentimes indeed, he takes the Matter more openly into his own Hand, and puniſhes them in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner, and in ſome ſignal way doth Execution upon them, when they think themſelves ſafe from fear, and far enough from danger.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98261:12"/>
            <p>How ſecure did <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> that wretched Pair of Wrong-doers, think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they had over-reached <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> and defrauded him of his Vineyard in a Court of Judicature, and under a Form of Juſtice, and with a ſhew of a Legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt him?</p>
            <p>Having this way gotten from him the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inheritance of his Father, they thought themſelves ſafe enough in the poſſeſſion of it, and free from any Harm that might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But a time of Recompence, and the Day of <hi>the Lord's Vengeance came upon them at laſt,</hi> and that with a <hi>Witneſs too,</hi> in a very Remarkable Way and Manner; for, as the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> had foretold, in the place where the Dogs licked the Blood of <hi>Naboth,</hi> there they alſo licked the Blood of <hi>Ahab;</hi> and there they not onely licked the Blood of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> but there they eat her up too, and left nothing of her Carcaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, but her Skull and her Feet, and the Palms of her Hands. And it is farther obſervable, that the evil which befell their Son King <hi>Joram,</hi> did over-take and ſeize
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98261:13"/>upon him in the Portion of <hi>Naboth</hi> the <hi>Jez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reelite;</hi> for there <hi>Jehu</hi> met him in his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious march againſt him, and there he ſmote him thorow the Heart with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and killed him; and there he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Body to be pulled down out of the Chariot, and caſt upon the open ground; ſo that he lay weltring in his own blood in that very plat of ground, which his Parents had defrauded <hi>Naboth</hi> of, and got unjuſtly from him. And indeed it is uſual with God, as the Hiſtories of all Ages will inform us, to puniſh thoſe that wrong others even in this World, either in their own perſons, or in their Poſterity, or in both, and that in ſome ſtrange and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner too: Nay, ſo ſtrangely is God provoled to Anger by this Sin of Wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Others, and ſo ſevere is he againſt it, that he many times plagues a Community, and puniſhes a whole Land and Nation for it; for we cannot read the Prophets with any heed and obſervation at all, but we muſt needs take notice that this is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned by moſt of them, as one of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98261:13"/>the main Sins and great Abominations for which God delivered up the <hi>Jews</hi> into their Enemies hands, The <hi>Jews,</hi> as we find up and down in the Prophets, were ſtrangely bent upon Violence and Wrong; their Houſes were full of deceit, and they were continually ſetting Traps, and laying Snares for their Brethren, and deviſing how they might over-reach and defraud one another; and for theſe ſins eſpecially it was, that the Wrath and Vengeance of God fell ſo heavy upon them: For it is very obſervable, that no ſins are ſo much inſiſted upon by the Prophets, as theſe, to be the Cauſe of their Deſolation, and of thoſe great and terrible Judgments that came upon them. Nay, it is yet farther obſervable, that in the Seventh Chapter of <hi>Zachariah, Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and <hi>Wrong-dealing</hi> are the onely ſins that are mentioned, for which God ſent them away into Captivity, and laid their Land deſolate and waſte: for the Prophet there tells them, that becauſe they refuſed to execute true Judgment, and would not ſhew Mercy and Compaſſion to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98261:14"/>but went on ſtill to oppreſs the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Fatherleſs, and the Stranger, and the Poor, and to imagine evil in their Hearts againſt their Brethren; therefore there came a great Wrath from the Lord of Hoſts: For theſe ſins ſuch a ſtorm of his Anger fell upon them, as ſcattered them with a Whirl-wind among all the Nations <hi>whom they knew not.</hi> But if thoſe that wrong others, and deal injuriouſly with them, ſhould eſcape the Vengeance of God in this World, and go down into their Graves, without having any remarkable Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted upon them here; yet ſhall they not for all this always go unpuniſhed; for the Wrath and Vengeance of God will purſue them into the other World, and there finally overtake them, and come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to the uttermoſt, and their latter end will be, that they ſhall periſh for ever. Tho theſe men may here by their wit or their Wealth, by thir power or their Friends, or by any other means eſcape the Judgment of Man, yet ſhall they not hereafter by all the Arts that they can uſe, eſcape the righteous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98261:14"/>Judgment of God: for God hath appointed a Day, wherein he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs; and when that Day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences is come, he will then render to every man according to his Deeds: to thoſe that have done juſtly, and have been righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in all their waies, and upright in all their Dealings, he will render Glory, and Honor, and Peace, and Immortality, and eternal Life: But to thoſe that have done wrong, and been unjuſt; to <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> and <hi>Deceivers;</hi> to the men that have been <hi>Injurious</hi> to their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and <hi>Inventers</hi> and <hi>Practiſers</hi> of evil things againſt them; <hi>He</hi> will render <hi>Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and <hi>Wrath, Tribulation</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh</hi> upon every <hi>Soul</hi> of them. <hi>They</hi> that have done <hi>Wrong,</hi> howſoever they may <hi>eſcape here,</hi> ſhall <hi>then</hi> receive in <hi>full meaſure</hi> for the wrong which they <hi>have done;</hi> their <hi>violent Dealing</hi> ſhall then fall down upon their own <hi>Heads</hi> in <hi>Eternal Showers</hi> of Vengeance, and <hi>God</hi> will for ever pay them home for all their <hi>Villanies</hi> and <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> which they have been guilty of. He will then make his whole <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> to ariſe againſt them, and will <hi>caſt</hi> the <hi>fury</hi> of his <hi>wrath</hi> upon them, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98261:15"/>
               <hi>puniſh them with everlaſting death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> from His Preſence, and be <hi>alwaies ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible</hi> in his doings towards them. He will then turn them into <hi>Hell,</hi> that frightful place of <hi>torments,</hi> where they muſt alwaies have their <hi>Habitation</hi> amongſt <hi>Devils</hi> and <hi>damned Spirits,</hi> and <hi>dwell</hi> with devouring <hi>Flames,</hi> and ſuffer the Vengeance of <hi>Eternal Fire,</hi> and for ever endure the heavieſt Plagues and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, that the vindicative <hi>Juſtice</hi> of an angry and incenſed God can heap upon them.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the <hi>Firſt</hi> thing, and I think have ſufficiently proved it to you by the Apoſtles, and by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arguments, that we muſt not do any manner of wrong to others, nor in any matter whatſoever deal injuriouſly with them. And now</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall bring this Duty yet farther home to you by ſome cloſe words of <hi>Application.</hi> And that this may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter done.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98261:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. Let us ſuffer a few words of Rebuke, and be perſwaded to hear a little, how very careleſs and negligent moſt of us are in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Duty. And then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us alſo ſuffer ſome words of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and be perſwaded for the time to come, to be more ſtrict and careful in the Performance of this Duty, than hitherto we have been.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us ſuffer a few words of Rebuke, and be perſwaded to hear a little how extreamly careleſs and negligent moſt of us are in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Duty. Though this Doctrine of not wronging others, is very clear and evident, both from Reaſon and Scripture, and a Doctrine that cannot be gainſaid, yet it is not received and entertained amongſt us, as it ought to be; for who is there that believes our report in this matter, that hath any regard to what we ſay in this thing? or that follows the Advice and Counſel that we give them in it? who are the Perſons, and where are they now almoſt to be found, that behave themſelves aright in this caſe, and are as careful as they ought to be, not to go beyond and defraud their Brethren? Are not the Hearts of moſt Men fully ſet in them to do Evil to one another? Do not their inward
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98261:16"/>Thoughts altogether run after Miſchief? And are they not continually plotting how they may compaſs their villanous Deſigns, and bring about thoſe pernitious Devices which they have devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the hurt of others? do not the generality of Men amongſt us make account that their Wits are their own, and that they may uſe them as they pleaſe for their own Intereſt and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage here? Do not they think that they may be as wiſe in their Generation, and as crafty as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they can, for their worldly Gains, and that to inrich themſelves, they may over-reach their Brethren in any of their Dealings and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns with them? And may not we make the ſame complaint of our Age, as <hi>Petrarch</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where doth of the Age wherein he lived; That Hunters and Fowlers cannot uſe greater cunning in laying their Nets and Snares for wild Beaſts and Fowls, than we do in ſetting Traps for one another? For what myſteries of cheating and cozenage have Men now-a-days got amongſt them? What Arts and Stratagems do they uſe to inveigle and enſnare thoſe that are unwary, and make a Prey of them? And how skilfull are they grown at all the ways of circumventing and over-reaching their Brethren? How ſubtile
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98261:16"/>and politick are they in their fraudulent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Courſes? What cunning Fetches and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices have they to wrong their Neighbours, and do them Harm? And how many Wiles and Inventions have they found out to work this their Iniquity by? So many indeed, that if I ſhould declare and ſpeak of them, they would be more than I ſhould be able to expreſs: Nay, it might juſtly bring a Man's Honeſty into ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to have the Skill, and be able to reckon them up. And therefore in a word; how bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy and active are the Men of this Generation in invading the Rights of their Neighbours, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring them in their Goods and Poſſeſſions? How greedy are they to inrich themſelves by Fraud and Deceit, and to enlarge their Eſtates, though it be by unjuſt Gain, and the Spoil of others? And how ready are they to take every Advantage that they can over their, Brethren, and to bring any kind of hurt and damage upon them, if by ſo doing they may any ways profit themſelves? But now,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us ſuffer ſome words of Exhortation alſo, and be perſwaded for the time to come to be more ſtrict and preciſe, more exact and punctual in the performance of this Duty, than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98261:17"/>hitherto we have been. Let us not hereafter any ways wrong our Brethren, nor defraud them in any matter, nor in any reſpect whatſoever do them the leaſt hurt; but let us walk honeſtly amongſt them, and in all things deal well and truly with them, and in no kind be injurious to them. Let us conſider what Obligations we have upon us not to wrong others: Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the Law of Nature it ſelf, that very Law that is written upon all our Hearts, teaches us not to do others any wrong: Let us conſider alſo, that the Laws of God are very full and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to the ſame purpoſe, and that the Old and the New Teſtament do abound with Precepts of this nature, that we muſt not harm others, nor imagine Miſchief in our Hearts againſt them, nor take any thing from them that doth of right belong to them. Nay, let us conſider, that the Commands of God do carry the buſineſs ſomewhat higher, and oblige us to love others, and to love them, though not in the ſame degree, yet with the ſame Truth and Sincerity of Love, that we do our ſelves, and to endeavour their good, as we would our own. And let us not break theſe Bonds aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor caſt away theſe Cords from us, nor ſin
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98261:17"/>againſt theſe Obligations which Nature, and the God of Nature hath laid upon us, not to be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and hurtful to others. But if theſe things will not ſignify any thing with us, as perhaps with many of us they may not; then let us conſider farther, how very great the danger is that we run, in doing wrong to others. Let us bethink our ſelves, that if we do injure and oppreſs, and defraud our Brethren, it is very likely that the Wrath of God will break out againſt us in this World, and that we ſhall be ſoundly puniſhed for it here; but to be ſure, we ſhall ſmart ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely for it hereafter: for then God will at laſt come in flaming Fire to take Vengeance on us, and will condemn us to the Puniſhments of the other World, to thoſe dreadful Pains and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there that will laſt to eternal Ages, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have an end. And let theſe Terrors of the Lord ſcare us out of all our unrighteous Practices, and fright us from all manner of Fraud and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice in our Dealings with one another. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we venture upon the wronging of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let us conſider it well in our minds, whether we can bear up and ſupport our ſelves under the Vengeance of God that will follow. Is our Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation a thing that we can lightly paſs over, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98261:18"/>make no great matter of? Can we withſtand the Power of God's Wrath, when he ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh all his Anger upon us? Can we for ever bear up under the weight of his Indignation, and without any anguiſh of Mind lie under the ſtrokes of his eternal Vengeance and Fury? Can our Hands be ſtrong in the day that an avenging God ſhall deal with us in his Juſtice, and ſet all his Terrors in array againſt us? Can our Hearts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure when he ſhall come in flaming Fire to take Vengeance on us, and turn us into Hell for the wrong that we have done? Can we then with any Comfort dwell in the midſt of devouring Flames and everlaſting Burnings? Can we then ſuffer the Vengeance of eternal Fire, without ſhrinking or being daunted at it? Can we then take any Contentment in the company of curſed Angels, and damned Spirits? And can we then chear up our ſelves againſt the horror and remorſe of our own guilty Conſciences, and with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence indure the Stings and Bitings of that Worm that never dies? If we cannot do theſe things, as to be ſure we cannot, then what deſperate Folly and Madneſs will it be for us to run into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of that Sin, which will moſt certainly be avenged upon us by ſuch diſmal Puniſhments as theſe are.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98261:18"/>
            <p>Surely, if we would ſometimes conſider how terrible God will be in his dealings with all inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perſons, and how dreadful the Works of his Vengeance will for ever be upon them, we durſt not defraud our Brethren, and do them Wrong ſo commonly as now we do.</p>
            <p>Would any dare to turn aſide the needy from Judgment, and take away the Right from the Poor, and make Widows their Prey, and rob the Fatherleſs, if they did but conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that a Father of the Fatherleſs, and a Judg of the Widows is God in his holy Habitation; and that from thence he ſees the Oppreſſion of the Poor, and hears the ſighing of the Needy, and will at length ariſe for their defence, and maintain their righteous Cauſe, and plague all thoſe that have harmed them wrongfully, and dealt injuriouſly with them?</p>
            <p>Would Men covet Fields, and take them by violence; and Houſes, and take them away: and ſo oppreſs a Man and his Houſe, even a Man and his Heritage? Could they be ſo very buſy and induſtrious as they are in invading the Rights of others; in defrauding the Brethren of their Goods, and injuring them in their Poſſeſſions; if they did but once take it into their Thoughts,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98261:19"/>that they muſt be called to a ſtrict account for theſe things before the righteous Judg of all the World, who loves Juſtice and Judgment, and will be ſure to puniſh the wrong-doer, and break in pieces the Oppreſſor, and ſpoil the Soul of all thoſe that have ſpoiled others?</p>
            <p>How durſt the ſubtile and the cunning Sinners hold faſt Deceit, and go on in their fraudulent and miſchievous Courſes? How durſt they deal ſo treacherouſly, and endeavour by their circumventing Skill to go beyond and over-reach their Neighbours, if they did but call to mind, that God ſees all their Fetches and their Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all their leſſer and greater Myſteries of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and will at laſt bring them into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for all thoſe wicked Arts and Stratagems, which they have ſo often made uſe of to enſnare the ignorant and unwary, and make them fall a Prey into their Nets?</p>
            <p>Would Men covet an evil Covetouſneſs to their Houſes, that they might ſet their Neſts on high? Would they go to raiſe their Families by that which they wrongfully take from others, if they conſidered that thir ill-gotten Wealth will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98261:19"/>bring ſuch a Curſe of God along with it into their Houſes, as will root out all their Increaſe, and quickly be the ruine and Dectruction of them and their Poſterity? Would they dare to ſuffer any unjuſt Gain to cleave to their Fingers? would they not preſently with all the haſte imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhake their Hands from holding of it, if they conſidered further, that the heaping up of this is but the laying up of Vengeance in Store, and the Treaſuring up of Wrath for themſelves againſt the great Day of Wrath?</p>
            <p>Would men be tampering in the very Courts of Juſtice, and be deviſing Subtilties there how they may Circumvent their Brethren, and thruſt them out of their apparent Rights, if they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that they muſt in another Court of Juſtice, and at Gods own Tribunal, give an Account of this, and there have the Sentence of Eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation Paſſed upon them for it?</p>
            <p>Would any Perſons have the boldneſs to be Givers or Takers of Bribes to Afflict the Innocent, if they conſidered that a God of Infinite Juſtice looks upon them, when their Hands are either opened to Receive, or Stretched out to give the Wages of Unrighteouſneſs, and that he will be an Avenger of all thoſe that uſe ſuch foul and Indirect Practices againſt their Brethren?</p>
            <p>With what Confidence could any men talk
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98261:20"/>deceitfully, and ſpeak in any matter to <hi>wreſt Judgment</hi> and <hi>pervert Equity,</hi> if they did but bethink themſelves that the God of Faithfulneſs and Truth knowes every word that is in their Mouths, and that he utterly abhorrs all thoſe that love Lying rather than to ſpeak Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and will at laſt Condemn them to thoſe eternal Flames, where they ſhall never be allowed one drop of Water to cool their falſe Tongues, which have framed Deceit? <hi>What ſhall be given unto thee? or what ſhall be done unto thee, thou falſe Tongue?</hi> It is <hi>David</hi>'s Queſtion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.3. And his Anſwer to it in the next Verſe is very dreadful: <hi>Sharp Arrows of the Mighty, with coals of Juniper:</hi> That is, as ſome of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Interpreters expound it, piercing Plagues here, and Hell fire hereafter: This ſhall be the Portion of thoſe men whoſe Tongues <hi>deviſe Miſchief,</hi> and who love <hi>all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring words</hi> that will do hurt.</p>
            <p>What fearfulneſs and trembling would ſeize upon the falſe Swearers? what an horrible dread would preſently overwhelm them, if they did but call to their remembrance that the juſt Lord hath taken notice of all their Perjuries, of all thoſe Oaths which they have Sworn falſely by his Name, to the hurt and Prejudice of others? And that he will not hold them Guiltleſs, nor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98261:20"/>ſuffer them to go Unpuniſhed for theſe hainous Crimes, but will moſt certainly let looſe the fierceneſs of his Anger and Diſpleaſure upon them, and purſue them with Wrath and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance all their dayes here, and throughout all the dayes of Eternity hereafter?</p>
            <p>And as for the high and mighty Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, the haughty and imperious Sinners, that have no regard at all either to the Laws of God or Man in this caſe, but do their Brethren hurt with as great a Confidence as others do them good; how would their Courage ſink, and their hearts fail them, if they would but take it into their Conſideration, that there is a great God above them to whom they muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for all the Hurt and Miſchief they have done, and that he will be no Reſpecter of their Perſons in Judgment, nor Spare them any more than the meaneſt Sinners in the day of his Wrath?</p>
            <p>And to draw to a Concluſion, for I think it is time ſo to do; Let us all be perſwaded ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frequently and ſeriouſly to conſider what this terrible place and Text of Scripture puts us in mind of, That the Lord will be a ſure and ſevere Avenger of all ſuch as <hi>go beyond</hi> and <hi>Defraud their Brethren</hi> in any matter; and let the fear of his Eternal Vengeance keep us
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98261:21"/>within the ſtricteſt Rules of Equity and Juſtice, and reſtrain us from doing the leaſt Injury or wrong to others. That we may eſcape that dreadful Wrath of his that is to come, let us forſake all our over-reaching, and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and deceitful Courſes; and let us do juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and live honeſtly, and neither deviſe nor practiſe any harm againſt our Brethren; and then when God comes to Judge the World, he will not be an <hi>Avenger,</hi> but a <hi>Rewarder</hi> of us; then we may all with Chearfulneſs and Comfort ſtand before his Judgment Seat at the laſt and final Judgment of all the World; for then the Judge of all the World will paſs a joyful Sentence upon us, and before the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt ſolemn Aſſembly that ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared before, all the Angels and all the Devils, and before all the Good men and all the Bad men of all Generations, will Pronounce us <hi>Bleſſed</hi> for evermore. And God grant that we may all be ſo Juſt to one another now, that the Lord may be Merciful to us all at that Day, and Receive us up into his Heavenly Kingdom, to be Partakers of all the Joys of it, and there to make our Eternal abode in his moſt glorious and delightful Preſence. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
